PARIKSHIT SUNIL DESHMUKH

pdeshmuk@buffalo.edu; [IN] https://www.linkedin.com/in/parikshitd92; [Git] https://github.com/parikshitdeshmukh; [Cell] +1 716 598 4517

SUMMARY

Software Developer and Analyst with 3 years and 6 months of experience in all phases of software development with Agile methodology. Proficient at development in Java, Python, SQL, REST API Web Services, JavaScript with hands-on experience on Machine Learning (libraries: TensorFlow, Keras, PyTorch, SciKit learn, SciPy, Numpy, Pandas) and Data Analysis. -- "Let it Train!"

EDUCATION

University at Buffalo, State University of New York

Aug 2017-Feb 2019

MS in Computer Science & Engineering (Al and Machine Learning)

Nagpur University, India

July 2009 - Aug 2013

Bachelors of Engineering

TECHNICAL SKILLS

• Languages: JAVA, MySQL, Python [Numpy, Scikit, SciPy, Pandas, Keras, TensorFlow, PyTorch], Django, R, jQuery, JUnit

Databases: MySQL, SQL Server 2008/2012, PostgreSQL, PL/SQL, JDBC

Data Science: Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Predictive Modelling, Statistical Data Mining, Data Analysis, LDA-QDA,

Seaborn, ggplot2, KNN, Random Forest, Amazon Web Services S3(cloud)

• Tools: Git, Maven, Pycharm, Intellij Idea, Eclipse, Docker, R Studio, PGAdmin, Visual studio

• **OS**: Unix,Linux, Mac OS

Other: REST Web Services API,JIRA, Scrum, Agile and Waterfall methodology

WORK EXPERIENCE

Cognizant Technology Solutions (Programmer Analyst)

Jan 2014 - Oct 2016

- Enhanced "MyPay" application for Cognizant employees to manage their financial section. Revamped using Python in Django framework
- Consumed external APIs and developed REST API using **Django REST Framework** and wrote numerous views (class based) and templates for page rendering.
- Built a Python application for a remedy system multi-class classification to intuitively classify the issue tickets raised by the
 users and allocate it to the respective operator handling that particular category of issues which reduced manual efforts by
 30-40%. (Tech: Multinomial Bayesian Network, tf-idf, Scikit learn, pandas, tensorflow)
- Architected and developed insurance applications in JAVA, Struts2 MVC, JavaScript and MySQL for integrating and managing the insured customers and potential customers data in MySQL database
- Wrote complex SQL queries for performing various CRUD operations, And, functions and procedures in PL/SQL for data processing and flow for the applications using JDBC API
- Utilized JavaScript and JQuery for validating the input given to the user interface and JUnit for testing the functionalities
- Followed Agile Methodology and used JIRA as Scrum management tool leading team of 3 new hires.
- Automated Geographic refresh process and optimized the PL/SQL procedure's run time by 20%
- Migrated the huddle meeting's task tracker board from Ms Excel to web-application which saved **30-40** % time for huddle meetings

The Advisory Board Company (Data Analyst)

Oct 2016 - Jun 2017

- Designed algorithms and configurations in Python for processing the member (patients) data based on the business requirement and loading it into PostgreSQL database; And, also feeding it to the front end for Care Managers to manage the patient's data.
- Automated the process of Quality Assurance Workbook generation by processing the incoming data, filtering it and populating
 the QA excel workbook, and sending mail with summary to the business analysts (+40% efficient)

PROJECTS

- Glasses Detection using Deep Convolutional Neural Network(Python, Deep CNN, PyTorch, TensorFlow):
 - o Implemented Deep CNN to determine if person in image is wearing glasses or not using TensorFlow and PyTorch
 - Used DCNN to train the model and SGD for hyperparameters tuning with Dropout regularizer for improving performance.
- Predicting Airlines delay and the best airport to fly out from (Python, Naive Bayes, Logistic Regression, AWS S3):
 - Performed Exploratory Data Analysis on the airlines dataset for multiple years and extracted the relevant features
 - Built predictive model on pickled data using Naive Bayes classifier and Logistic Regression on top of Gaussian Basis functions and validated using Early Stopping method. Tested the model to predict city's best airport with minimum flight delay.
- Handwritten digit classification (Convolutional Neural Network, TensorFlow, Adam Optimizer): Built and trained a Logistic
 Regression and Convolutional Neural Network model for classifying handwritten digits and achieved accuracy of 99% with CNN
 model. Implemented Backpropagation for 3 layer neural net with Softmax and Tanh activation function.
- Learning to rank on query-URL pair for Information Retrieval (Python, Linear Regression, SGD):
 - Performed predictive analysis on Microsoft LETOR 4.0 dataset using Closed form solution and Stochastic Gradient Descent algorithms to gain the minimum RMSE of 0.5.
 - Incorporated Gaussian Basis function to deal with nonlinear data and, Early Stopping for the most optimal solution.
- JUNK Filter (Python): Developed Junk mail filter for irrelevant updates coming from batch job's completion using Bayesian classifier
- **Knowledge Transition for new employee (JAVA)**: Architected and developed a module in Django on-boarding of the new employees in project which reduced human efforts by 20-30%.